{
  "reference_number": "11164",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "2050 is much too far away. People are frightened by global warming. We need to see significant progress before the next election."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "Net zero by 2025 preferred."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "I have no objection to helping other countries plant trees, but we must achieve carbon neutrality for ourselves within our own\n borders."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Not unless it is revised to meet the target sooner."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "They need to be very ambitious budgets, and we need regular updates within the five year periods."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "They should only be changed in order to reach goals sooner."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "They should only be changed in order to reach goals sooner."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "You also need to consider the impact of the slowness of implementing effective climate action on children, young people and their\nmental health. I suggest input from the Office of the Children's Commissioner."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "With all the urgency of a war effort, because this is about survival."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The fear of young people needs to be directly considered. They do not believe they will have a future. Ways of making rapid action\nand regularly reporting this action to young people to restore their hope are really important. I suggest input from the Office of the\n\nChildren's Commissioner."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "And adapting to carbon neutral lifestyles and ways of doing business."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Also, a regularly updated education function to help households and businesses make the wisest decisions about lowering their\n\ncarbon impact. This is challenging at present because there is a lot of contradictory information available, including outdated\ninformation."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I do not wish my address, phone number or email address to be made public. Emotional impact of slow progress towards carbon\nneutrality I am a teacher and a parent. I believe that a sense of despair about global warming is impacting on the mental health of\n\nyoung people right now. I believe that global warming is already claiming lives in New Zealand, because the level of anxiety and\nsadness which children and young people feel about the failing climate reduces their resilience to other stressors, making them\n\nmore vulnerable to suicide. My conversations with children and young adults tell me that most young people today do not expect to\ngrow old. They expect their cause of death to be climate-related. I feel that our government is not doing nearly enough to address\nthe threat of global warming. We are moving at a snail’s pace to address a problem which is increasing exponentially. We need to see\n\nweekly progress reports showing actual progress towards sustainability. We need both the appearance and the reality of acting fast\non this, for the sake of our young people’s sense of having a future to work towards and to look forward to.\n\n\n\n\n You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
